<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE tmx SYSTEM "tmx14.dtd">
<tmx version="1.4">
  <header creationtool="OmegaT" o-tmf="OmegaT TMX" adminlang="EN-US" datatype="plaintext" creationtoolversion="6.0.0_0_1bf1729c" segtype="sentence" srclang="en"/>
  <body>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Chapter 8 Pivot Tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Capítulo 8 Tabelas Dinâmicas</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc Guide</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Guia do Calc</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Chapter 8Using Pivot Tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Capítulo 8Tabelas dinâmicas</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Introduction</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Introdução</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Many requests for spreadsheet support are the result of using complicated formulas and solutions to solve simple day-to-day problems.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Muitos pedidos de suporte a planilhas de trabalho são o resultado do uso de fórmulas e soluções complicadas para resolver problemas simples do dia a dia.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For more efficient and effective solutions, use the pivot table, a tool for combining, comparing, and analyzing large amounts of data easily.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para soluções mais eficientes e eficazes, use a tabela dinâmica, uma ferramenta para combinar, comparar e analisar facilmente grandes quantidades de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Using pivot tables, you can view different summaries of the source data, display the details of areas of interest, and create reports, whether you are a beginner, an intermediate, or an advanced user.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Usando tabelas dinâmicas, pode-se visualizar diferentes resumos dos dados de origem, exibir os detalhes de áreas de interesse e criar relatórios, seja um usuário iniciante, intermediário ou avançado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In addition you can create a pivot chart to view a graphical representation of the data in a pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Além disso, pode-se criar um gráfico dinâmico para visualizar uma representação gráfica dos dados em uma tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>database preconditions</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>pré-condições do bando de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Database preconditions</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pré-condições do banco de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To work with a pivot table, you need a list of raw data, similar to a database table, consisting of rows (data sets) and columns (data fields).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para trabalhar com uma tabela dinâmica, precisa-se de uma lista de dados brutos, semelhante a uma tabela de banco de dados, consistindo em linhas (conjuntos de dados) e colunas (campos de dados).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The field names are in the first row above the list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os nomes dos campos estão na primeira linha acima da lista.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The data source could be an external file or database.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A fonte de dados pode ser um arquivo externo ou banco de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For the simplest case, where data is contained in a Calc spreadsheet, Calc offers sorting functions that do not require the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para o caso mais simples, onde os dados estão contidos em uma planilha de trabalho do Calc, o Calc oferece funções de ordenação que não requerem a tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For processing data in lists, Calc needs to know where in the spreadsheet the list is.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para processar dados em listas, o Calc precisa saber onde a lista está na planilha de trabalho.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The list can be anywhere in the sheet, in any position.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A lista pode estar em qualquer lugar da planilha, em qualquer posição.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A spreadsheet can contain several unrelated lists.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Uma planilha de trabalho pode conter várias listas não relacionadas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc recognizes your lists automatically.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Calc reconhece suas listas automaticamente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>It uses the following logic: Starting from the cell you have selected (which must be within the list), Calc checks the surrounding cells in all four directions (left, right, above, below).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ele usa a seguinte lógica: A partir da célula que se selecionou (que deve estar dentro da lista), o Calc verifica as células ao redor em todas as quatro direções (esquerda, direita, acima, abaixo).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The border is recognized if the program discovers an empty row or column, or if it hits the left or upper border of the spreadsheet.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A borda é reconhecida se o programa descobrir uma linha ou coluna vazia, ou se atingir a borda esquerda ou superior da planilha de trabalho.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This means that the described functions can only work correctly if there are no empty rows or columns in the list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Isso significa que as funções descritas só podem funcionar corretamente se não houver linhas ou colunas vazias na lista.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Avoid empty lines (for example for formatting).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Evite linhas vazias (por exemplo, para formatação).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can format the list by using cell formats.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se formatar a lista usando formatos de células.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To make sure that Calc automatically recognizes a list correctly, check that there are no empty rows or empty columns within the list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para ter certeza de que o Calc reconhece automaticamente uma lista corretamente, verifique se não há linhas vazias ou colunas vazias na lista.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you select more than one cell before creating a pivot table, then Calc’s automatic list recognition logic is not applied.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se selecionar mais de uma célula antes de criar uma tabela dinâmica, a lógica de reconhecimento de lista automática do Calc não será aplicada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Instead, Calc assumes that the pivot table is to be created using exactly the cells that you selected.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Em vez disso, o Calc assume que a tabela dinâmica deve ser criada usando exatamente as células que se selecionou.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Always select only one cell before initiating creation of a pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Sempre selecione apenas uma célula antes de iniciar a criação de uma tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This allows Calc to automatically determine the full scope of your data list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Isso permite que o Calc determine automaticamente o escopo completo de sua lista de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A relatively common source of errors is to inadvertently declare a list by mistake and then to sort that list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Uma fonte relativamente comum de erros é declarar inadvertidamente uma lista por engano e, em seguida, classificá-la.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you select multiple cells—for example, a whole column—then the sorting mixes up the data that should be together in one row.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se selecionar várias células – por exemplo, uma coluna inteira – a ordenação mistura os dados que deveriam estar juntos em uma linha.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In addition to these formal aspects, the logical structure of the list is also very important.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Além desses aspectos formais, a estrutura lógica da lista também é muito importante.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc lists must have the normal form; that is, they must have a simple linear structure.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Listas do Calc devem ter a forma normal; ou seja, eles devem ter uma estrutura linear simples.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>When entering the data, do not add outlines, groups, or summaries.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ao inserir os dados, não adicione contornos, grupos ou resumos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Here are some mistakes commonly made by inexperienced spreadsheet users:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Aqui estão alguns erros mais comuns cometidos por usuários inexperientes em planilhas de trabalho:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You made several unnecessary sheets; for example, a sheet for each group of articles.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Fazer várias planilhas desnecessárias; por exemplo, uma planilha para cada grupo de artigos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this case, analyses are only possible within each group.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Neste caso, as análises são só possível dentro de cada grupo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In a sales list, instead of only one column for the amount, you made a column for the amounts for each employee.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Em uma lista de vendas, em vez de apenas uma coluna para o valor, faça uma coluna para os valores de cada funcionário.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this case, the system will have difficulty grouping data from the various columns together.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nesse caso, o sistema terá dificuldade em agrupar os dados das várias colunas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Thus, an analysis with the pivot table would no longer be possible.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Assim, uma análise com a tabela dinâmica não seria mais possível.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>All data must be entered into the same column for the pivot table to be able to analyze it.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Todos os dados devem ser inseridos na mesma coluna para que a tabela dinâmica possa analisá-los.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You entered the amounts in chronological order.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se inseriu os valores em ordem cronológica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>At the end of each month, you made a sum total.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No final de cada mês, se fez uma soma total.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this case, sorting the list for different criteria is not possible because the pivot table will treat the sum totals the same as any other value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nesse caso, classificar a lista para critérios diferentes não é possível porque a tabela dinâmica tratará os totais da soma da mesma forma que qualquer outro valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Getting monthly results is one of the very fast and easy features of the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Obter resultados mensais é um dos recursos muito rápidos e fáceis da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>data sources</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>fonte de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Data sources</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Fontes de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The possible data sources for the pivot table are a Calc spreadsheet or an external data source that is registered in LibreOffice.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As fontes de dados possíveis para a tabela dinâmica são uma planilha de trabalho do Calc ou uma fonte de dados externa registrada no LibreOffice.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc spreadsheet</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Planilha de trabalho do Calc</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Analyzing a list in a Calc spreadsheet is the simplest and most often used case.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Analisar uma lista em uma planilha de trabalho do Calc é o caso mais simples e usado com mais frequência.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Lists might be updated regularly or the data might be imported from a different application.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As listas podem ser atualizadas regularmente ou os dados podem ser importados de um aplicativo diferente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The list data might be entered directly into the spreadsheet or copied from another file or application.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os dados da lista podem ser inseridos diretamente na planilha ou copiados de outro arquivo ou aplicativo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can also use a Web Page Query input filter to insert data from a HTML file, a CSV file, a Calc spreadsheet, or a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se também usar um filtro de entrada Consulta de página da Web para inserir dados de um arquivo HTML, um arquivo CSV, uma planilha de trabalho do Calc ou uma planilha de trabalho do Microsoft Excel.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>See Chapter 10, Linking Data, for more information.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Consulte o Capítulo 10, Vincular dados, para obter mais informações.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The behavior of Calc while inserting data from a different application depends on the format of the data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O comportamento do Calc ao inserir dados de um aplicativo diferente depende do formato dos dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the data is in a common spreadsheet format, it is copied directly into Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se os dados estiverem em um formato de planilha de trabalho comum, eles serão copiados diretamente para o Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>However, if the data is in plain text format, the Text Import dialog appears after you select the file containing the data; see Chapter 1, Introduction, for more more information about this dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No entanto, se os dados estiverem em formato de texto sem formatação, a caixa de diálogo Importação de texto aparecerá após selecionar o arquivo que contém os dados; consulte o Capítulo 1, Introdução, para obter mais informações sobre esta caixa de diálogo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Registered data source</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Fonte de dados registrada</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A registered data source is a connection to data held in a database outside of LibreOffice.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Uma fonte de dados registrada é uma conexão a dados mantidos em um banco de dados fora do LibreOffice.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>When using a registered data source, the data to be analyzed will not be saved in the spreadsheet; Calc will always use the data from the original source.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ao usar uma fonte de dados registrada, os dados a serem analisados não serão salvos no a planilha de trabalho; o Calc vai sempre usar os dados da fonte original.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc is able to use many different data sources in addition to databases that are created and maintained with LibreOffice Base.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Calc é capaz de usar muitas fontes de dados diferentes, além de bancos de dados que são criados e mantidos com o LibreOffice Base.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For more information, see Chapter 10, Linking Data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para obter mais informações, consulte o Capítulo 10, Vinculando dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Using shortcuts</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Usando atalhos</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you use pivot tables often in Calc, you might find the frequent use of the built-in menu paths inconvenient.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se usa tabelas dinâmicas com frequência no Calc, pode achar o uso frequente dos caminhos de menu embutidos inconveniente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In some cases built-in keyboard shortcuts are already defined; see Appendix A, Keyboard Shortcuts.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Em alguns casos, os atalhos de teclado integrados já estão definidos; consulte o Apêndice A, Atalhos de teclado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>An example is the F12 function key, which groups a selected data range.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um exemplo é a tecla de função F12, que agrupa um intervalo de dados selecionado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In some other cases, the built-in toolbars already provide relevant icons.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Em alguns outros casos, as barras de ferramentas integradas já fornecem ícones relevantes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>An example is the Insert or Edit Pivot Table icon on the Standard toolbar.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um exemplo é o ícone Inserir ou editar tabela dinâmica na barra de ferramentas padrão.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In addition to using the built-in keyboard shortcuts and toolbar icons, you can also define your own.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Além de usar os atalhos de teclado integrados e os ícones da barra de ferramentas, pode-se também definir os seus próprios.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>See Chapter 14, Setting up and Customizing, for instructions.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Consulte o Capítulo 14, Configurando e Personalizando, para obter instruções.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Creating a pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Criação de uma tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you want Calc to automatically determine the full extent of the raw data list, then select a single cell within this list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se deseja que o Calc determine automaticamente a extensão total da lista de dados brutos, selecione uma única célula nesta lista.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you want to explicitly define the extent of the raw data list, then select all relevant cells.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se deseja definir explicitamente a extensão da lista de dados brutos, selecione todas as células relevantes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>With the cell (or cells) selected, create the pivot table by selecting Insert &gt; Pivot Table on the Menu bar, selecting Data &gt; Pivot Table &gt; Insert or Edit on the Menu bar, or clicking the Insert or Edit Pivot Table icon on the Standard toolbar.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com a célula (ou células) selecionada, crie a tabela dinâmica selecionando Inserir &gt; Tabela dinâmica na barra de menu, selecionando Dados &gt; Tabela dinâmica &gt; Inserir ou editar na barra de menus ou clicando no ícone Inserir ou editar tabela dinâmica na barra de ferramentas Padrão.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc displays the Select Source dialog (Figure 1), where you can choose between using the selected data cells, a range of cells that has already been named, or a data source that has already been registered with LibreOffice.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Calc exibe a caixa de diálogo Selecionar a origem dos dados (1), onde pode-se escolher entre usar as células de dados selecionadas, um intervalo de células que já foi nomeado ou uma fonte de dados que já foi registrada no LibreOffice.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>See Chapter 13, Calc as a Database, for more information about named ranges.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Consulte o Capítulo 13, Calc como um banco de dados, para obter mais informações sobre intervalos nomeados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>See Chapter 10, Linking Data, for more information about linking to registered data sources.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Consulte o Capítulo 10, Vinculando dados, para obter mais informações sobre como vincular a fontes de dados registradas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 1: Select Source dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 1: caixa de diálogo Selecionar a origem dos dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click OK on the Select Source dialog to display the Pivot Table Layout dialog, which is described in the next section.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique em OK na caixa de diálogo Selecionar origem dos dados para exibir a caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica, que é descrita na próxima seção.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The function of the pivot table is managed in two places: first, in the Pivot Table Layout dialog; and second, through manipulations of the result in the spreadsheet.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A função da tabela dinâmica é gerenciada em dois locais: primeiro, na caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica; e segundo, por meio de manipulações do resultado na planilha de trabalho.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This section describes the Pivot Table Layout dialog in detail.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esta seção descreve a caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica em detalhes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Tip</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Dica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To access the Pivot Table Layout dialog again after initial creation of a pivot table, left-click in any cell of the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para acessar a caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica novamente após a criação inicial de uma tabela dinâmica, clique com o botão esquerdo em qualquer célula da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Then select Insert &gt; Pivot Table on the Menu bar, or select Data &gt; Pivot Table &gt; Insert or Edit on the Menu bar, or click the Insert or Edit Pivot Table icon on the Standard toolbar, or right-click in any cell of the pivot table and select the Properties option in the context menu.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Então selecione Inserir &gt; Tabela Dinâmica na barra de menu ou selecione Dados &gt; Tabela Dinâmica &gt; Inserir ou Editar na barra de menu ou clique no ícone Inserir ou editar tabela dinâmica na barra de ferramentas padrão, ou clique com o botão direito em qualquer célula da tabela dinâmica e selecione a opção Propriedades no menu de contexto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>defining the layout of the pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>definindo o leiaute da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>caixa de diálogo Tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Basic layout</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Leiaute básico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the Pivot Table Layout dialog (Figure 2) are four areas that show the layout of the resulting pivot table:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica (2) são quatro áreas que mostram o Leiaute da tabela dinâmica resultante:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Filters</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Filtros</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Column Fields</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Campos de coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Row Fields</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Campos de linha</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Data Fields</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Campos de Dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Beside these four areas is another area labeled Available Fields that contains the names of the fields in the source data list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ao lado dessas quatro áreas está outra área rotulada Campos disponíveis que contém os nomes dos campos na lista de dados de origem.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To choose a layout, drag and drop the fields from the Available Fields area to the other four areas.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para escolher um leiaute, arraste e solte os campos da área Campos disponíveis para as outras quatro áreas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Data Fields area must contain at least one field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A área Campos de dados deve conter pelo menos um campo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Advanced users can use more than one field here.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os usuários avançados podem usar mais de um campo aqui.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For the fields in the Data Fields area, an aggregate function is used.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para os campos na área Campos de dados, uma função agregada é usada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For example, if you move the Sales Value field into the Data Fields area, it initially appears there as Sum – Sales Value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por exemplo, se mover o campo Valor de venda para a área Campos de Dados, inicialmente aparece lá como Soma – Valor de venda.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 2: Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 2: caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela Dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Row and column fields indicate from which groups the result will be sorted.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os campos de linha e coluna indicam de quais grupos o resultado será classificado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Often more than one field is used at a time to get partial sums for rows or columns.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Frequentemente, mais de um campo é usado por vez para obter somas parciais de linhas ou colunas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The order of the fields gives the order of the sums from overall to specific.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A ordem dos campos fornece a ordem das somas de geral para específico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For example, if you drag Region and Employee into the Row Fields area, the sum will be divided into the regions.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por exemplo, se arrastar Região e Funcionário na área Campos de linha, a soma será dividida nas regiões.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Within the regions will be the listing for the different employees (Figure 3).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Dentro das regiões estará a lista para os diferentes funcionários (3)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 3: Field order for analysis and resulting layout of pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 3: Ordem dos campos para análise e leiaute resultante da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Fields that are placed into the Filters area appear at the top of the resulting pivot table as a drop-down list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os campos que são colocados na área Filtros aparecem no topo da tabela dinâmica resultante como uma lista suspensa.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The summary in the result takes into account only that part of the base data that you have selected.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resumo no resultado leva em consideração apenas aquela parte dos dados básicos que se selecionou.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For example, if you include Employee in the Filters area, you can filter the result shown for each employee.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por exemplo, se incluir Funcionário na área Filtros, pode-se filtrar o resultado mostrado para cada funcionário.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To move a field from an area, just drag it to a new area.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para mover um campo de uma área, basta arrastá-lo para uma nova área.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To remove a field from the Filters, Column Fields, Row Fields, or Data Fields areas, drag it to the Available Fields area.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para remover um campo das áreas Filtros, Campos de coluna, Campos de linha, ou Campos de Dados, arraste-o para a área Campos Disponíveis.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Tip</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Dica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To rapidly move a selected field from one area of the Pivot Table Layout dialog to another, press the Alt+letter on the keyboard that corresponds to the underlined letter in the target area’s label.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para mover rapidamente um campo selecionado de uma área da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica para outra, tecle Alt+letra que corresponde à letra sublinhada na etiqueta da área de destino.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>By default, Calc inserts a Data field into the Column Fields area.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por padrão, o Calc insere um campo Dados para a área Campos de coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Data field can be moved between the Column Fields and Row Fields areas as required.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O campo Dados pode ser movido entre as áreas Campos de coluna e Campos de linha conforme necessário.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Depending on its position within the list of fields in its area, the Data field may lead to a button labeled Data appearing in the results of the pivot table, affecting the layout of the results.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Dependendo de sua posição na lista de Campos em sua área, o campo Dados pode levar a um botão rotulado Dados aparecendo nos resultados da tabela dinâmica, afetando o leiaute dos resultados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you do not wish to use this facility, simply place the Data field at the bottom of the list of fields in its area.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se não deseja usar esta facilidade, basta colocar o campo Dados na parte inferior da lista de campos em sua área.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>additional options</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>opçoes adicionais</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>caixa de diálogo Tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>More options</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Mais opções</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To expand the Pivot Table Layout dialog and show more options, click the expansion symbol (plus or triangle sign) adjacent to the Options and Source and Destination labels (Figure 4).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para expandir a caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica e mostrar mais opções, clique no símbolo de expansão (sinal de mais ou triângulo) adjacente aos rótulos Opções e Origem e Destino (4).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Ignore empty rows</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ignorar linhas vazias</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the source data is not in the recommended form, this option tells the pivot table to ignore empty rows.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se os dados de origem não estiverem no formato recomendado, esta opção informa à tabela dinâmica para ignorar as linhas vazias.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 4: Expanded area of the Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 4: Área expandida da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Identify categories</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Identificar categorias</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>With this option selected, if the source data has missing entries in a list and does not meet the recommended data structure (as in Figure 5for example), the pivot table adds it to the listed category above it.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com esta opção selecionada, se os dados de origem tiverem entradas ausentes em uma lista e não atenderem à estrutura de dados recomendada (como na 5por exemplo), a tabela dinâmica o adiciona à categoria listada acima dela.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If this option is not chosen, then the pivot table inserts (empty).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se esta opção não for escolhida, a tabela dinâmica insere (vazio).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 5: Example of data with missing entries in Column A</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 5: Exemplo de dados com entradas ausentes na coluna A</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The option Identify categories ensures that in this example rows 3 and 4 are included for Apples and that row 6 is included for Pears (Figure 6).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A opção Identificar categorias garante que neste exemplo as linhas 3 e 4 sejam incluídas para maçãs e que a linha 6 seja incluída para peras (6).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 6: Pivot table result with Identify categories selected</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 6: Resultado da tabela dinâmica com Identificar categorias selecionado</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Without category recognition, the pivot table shows an (empty) category (Figure 7).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Sem o reconhecimento da categoria, a tabela dinâmica mostra uma categoria (vazio) (7).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 7: Pivot table result without Identify categories selected</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 7: Resultado da tabela dinâmica sem Identificar categorias selecionado</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Logically, the behavior with category recognition is better.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Logicamente, o comportamento com reconhecimento de categoria é melhor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A list showing missing entries is also less useful, because you cannot use functions such as sorting or filtering.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Uma lista que mostra as entradas ausentes também é menos útil, porque não se pode usar funções como ordenação ou filtragem.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Total columns, Total rows</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Totalizar colunas, totalizar as linhas</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>With these options you can decide if the pivot table shows an extra row with the sums of each column, or if it adds on the very right a column with the sums of each row.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com estas opções pode-se decidir se a tabela dinâmica mostra uma linha extra, com as somas de cada coluna, ou se adiciona à direita uma coluna com as somas de cada linha.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In some cases, an added total sum is meaningless, for example if the entries are accumulated or the result of comparisons.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Em alguns casos, uma soma total adicionada não tem sentido, por exemplo, se as entradas forem acumuladas ou o resultado de comparações.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Add filter</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Adicionar filtro</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Use this option to add or hide the cell labeled Filter above the pivot table results.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Use esta opção para adicionar ou esconder a célula rotulada Filtro acima dos resultados da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This conveniently provides additional filtering options within the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Isso fornece convenientemente opções de filtragem adicionais na tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For more information, see “Filtering” on page 24.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para mais informações, veja “Filtragem” abaixo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The filtering provided through the Add filter option is independent of the filtering provided by including fields in the Filters area of the Pivot Table Layout dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A filtragem fornecida por meio da opção Adicionar filtro é independente da filtragem fornecida, incluindo campos na área Filtros da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Enable drill to details</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ativar análise de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>With this option enabled, if you double-click on a single data cell in the pivot table result, including a cell produced from Total columns or Total rows, a new sheet opens giving a detailed listing of the individual entry.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com esta opção ativada, se clicar duas vezes em uma única célula de dados no resultado da tabela dinâmica, incluindo uma célula produzida a partir de Total de colunas ou Total de linhas, uma nova planilha é aberta fornecendo uma lista detalhada da entrada individual.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you double-click on a cell in either a row or column field area, then the Show Detail dialog opens (Figure 39).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se clicar duas vezes em uma célula em um campo de linha ou coluna área, então a caixa de diálogo Mostrar detalhe é aberta (29).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If this function is disabled, the double-click will keep its usual edit function within a spreadsheet.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se esta função estiver desabilitada, o clique duplo manterá sua função de edição usual em uma planilha de trabalho.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For more information, see “Drilling (showing details)” on page 23.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para mais informações, veja “Detalhar (mostrar os detalhes)” abaixo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Source</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Origem</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Selection field in this area shows the sheet name and the range of cells containing the raw data for the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Campo Seleção nesta área mostra o nome da planilha e o intervalo de células que contêm os dados brutos da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the source spreadsheet contains any named ranges, these can be selected through the Named range option.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se a planilha de origem contiver quaisquer intervalos nomeados, eles podem ser selecionados por meio da opção Intervalo nomeado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Destination</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Destino</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The controls in this area define where the result will be shown.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os controles nesta área definem onde o resultado será mostrado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selecting New sheet adds a new sheet to the spreadsheet file and places the results there.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecionando Nova planilha adiciona uma nova planilha de trabalho ao arquivo de planilha e coloca os resultados lá.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The new sheet is named using the format Pivot Table_sheetname_X; where X is the number of the table created, 1 for first, 2 for second, and so on.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A nova planilha de trabalho é nomeada usando o formato Tabela dinâmica_Planilha_X; onde X é o número da tabela criada, 1 para o primeiro, 2 para o segundo e assim por diante.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For a sheet named Sales List, the new sheet for the first pivot table produced would be named Pivot Table_Sales List_1.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para uma planilha chamada Lista de Vendas, a nova planilha da primeira tabela dinâmica produzida seria nomeada Tabela dinâmica_ Lista de Vendas_1.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Each new sheet is inserted next to the source sheet.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Cada nova planilha é inserida ao lado da planilha de origem.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the target spreadsheet contains any named ranges, these can be selected with the Named range option.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se a planilha de trabalho de destino contém quaisquer intervalos nomeados, eles podem ser selecionados com a opção Intervalo nomeado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Selection field in this area shows the sheet name and the range of cells for the pivot table’s results.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O campo Seleção nesta área mostra o nome da planilha e o intervalo de células para os resultados da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Tip</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Dica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To display the pivot table on the same sheet as the raw data, check the Selection option in the Destination area, click the Shrink button to the right of the Selection field, click at an appropriate cell in an empty area of the sheet, click the Expand button, and click OK on the Pivot Table Layout dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para exibir a tabela dinâmica na mesma planilha dos dados brutos, verifique a opção Seleção na área Destino, clique no botão Encolher à direita do campo Seleção, clique em uma célula apropriada em uma área vazia da planilha, clique no botão Expandir e clique OK na caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>More settings for the fields: Field options</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Mais configurações para os campos: Opções de campo</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The options discussed in the previous section are valid for the pivot table in general.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As opções discutidas na seção anterior são válidas para a tabela dinâmica em geral.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can also change settings for any field that is currently included in the pivot table layout.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se também alterar as configurações de qualquer campo que esteja atualmente incluído no Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Change a field’s settings by double-clicking that field within the Filters, Column Fields, Row Fields, or Data Fields areas of the Pivot Table Layout dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Altere as configurações de um campo clicando duas vezes nesse campo dentro da área Filtros, Campos de coluna, Campos de linha ou Campos de dados da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Double-clicking a field within the Available Fields area has no effect.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clicar duas vezes em um campo dentro da área Campos disponíveis não tem efeito.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The options available for fields in the Data Fields area differ from those for fields in the other three areas.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As opções disponíveis para campos na área Campos de dados diferem daquelas para campos nas outras três áreas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>data field options</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>opções para campos de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>caixa de diálogo Tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Options for data fields</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Opções para campos de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Double-click a field in the Data Fields area of the Pivot Table Layout dialog to access the Data Field dialog shown in Figure 8.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique duas vezes em um campo na área Campos de dados da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica para acessar a caixa de diálogo Campo de dados mostrada na 8.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the Data Field dialog, you can select the function to be used to accumulate the values from the data source.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na caixa de diálogo Campo de dados, pode-se selecionar a função a ser usada para acumular os valores da fonte de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>While you often use the Sum function, other functions (like standard deviation or a counting function) are also available.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Embora se use frequentemente a função Soma, outras funções (como desvio padrão ou uma função de contagem) também estão disponíveis.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For example, the counting function can be useful for non-numerical data fields.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por exemplo, a função de contagem pode ser útil para campos de dados não numéricos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select the Show items without data option to include empty columns and rows in the results table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione a opção Mostrar itens sem dados para incluir colunas e linhas vazias na tabela de resultados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click the expansion symbol (plus sign or triangle) to expand the Displayed value section of the dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique no símbolo de expansão (sinal de mais ou triângulo) para expandir a seção Valor exibido da caixa de diálogo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 8: Expanded dialog for a data field</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 8: Caixa de diálogo expandida para um campo de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the Displayed value section, you can choose other possibilities for analysis using the aggregate function.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na seção Valor exibido, pode-se escolher outras possibilidades de análise usando a função de agregação.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Depending on the setting for Type, you may have to choose definitions for Base field and Base item.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Dependendo da configuração para Tipo, pode-se ter que escolher definições para Campo base e Item de base.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 9: Example choices for Base field and Base item</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 9: Exemplo de escolhas para Campo base e Item base</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Table 1below lists the possible types of displayed value and associated base field and base item, together with notes on usage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A 1abaixo lista os possíveis tipos de valor exibido e campo base associado e item base, junto com nota s no uso.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Table 1: Description of Displayed value options on the Data Field dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Tabela 1: Descrição das opções de valores exibidos na caixa de diálogo Campo de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Type</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Tipo</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Base field</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Campo base</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Base item</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Item base</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Analysis</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Análises</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Simple use of the chosen aggregate function (for example, Sum).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Uso simples da função de agregação escolhida (por exemplo, Soma).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Difference from</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Diferença de</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selection of a field from the data source of the pivot table (for example, Employee).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Seleção de um campo da fonte de dados da tabela dinâmica (por exemplo, Funcionário).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selection of an element from the selected base field (for example, Brigitte)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Seleção de um elemento do campo base selecionado (por exemplo, Brigite)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The result is the difference between the result of the base field and the base item (for example, sales volume of the other employees against the sales volume of Brigitte; see Figure 10).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resultado é a diferença entre o resultado do campo base e o item base (por exemplo, o volume de vendas dos outros funcionários em relação ao volume de vendas do Carlos; consulte a 10)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If previous item or next item is specified as the Base item, the reference value is the result for the next visible member of the base field, in the base field’s sort order.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>E se item anterior ou próximo item é especificado como o Item de base, o valor de referência é o resultado para o próximo membro visível do campo base, na ordenação do campo base.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>% of</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>% de</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selection of a field from the data source of the pivot table (for example, Employee)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Seleção de um campo da fonte de dados da tabela dinâmica (por exemplo, Funcionário)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selection of an element from the selected base field (for example, Brigitte)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Seleção de um elemento do campo base selecionado (por exemplo, Brigite)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The result is a percentage ratio of the value of the base field to the base item (for example, sales result of the other employees relative to the sales result of Brigitte; see Figure 11).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resultado é uma proporção percentual do valor do campo base para o item base (por exemplo, o resultado das vendas dos outros funcionários em relação ao resultado das vendas de Carlos; consulte a 11)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If previous item or next item is specified as the Base item, the reference value is the result for the next visible member of the base field, in the base field’s sort order.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>E se item anterior ou próximo item é especificado como o Item de base, o valor de referência é o resultado para o próximo membro visível do campo base, na ordenação do campo base.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>% difference from</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>% diferença de</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selection of a field from the data source of the pivot table (for example, Employee)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Seleção de um campo da fonte de dados da tabela dinâmica (por exemplo, Funcionário)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selection of an element from the selected base field (for example, Brigitte)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Seleção de um elemento do campo base selecionado (por exemplo, Brigite)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>From each result, its reference value is subtracted, and the difference is divided by the reference value (for example, sales of the other employees as relative difference from the sales of Brigitte; see Figure 12).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>De cada resultado, seu valor de referência é subtraído e a diferença é dividida pelo valor de referência (por exemplo, vendas dos outros funcionários como diferença relativa das vendas de Carlos; ver 12)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If previous item or next item is specified as the Base item, the reference value is the result for the next visible member of the base field, in the base field’s sort order.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>E se item anterior ou próximo item é especificado como o Item de base, o valor de referência é o resultado para o próximo membro visível do campo base, na ordenação do campo base.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Running total in</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Executando total em</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selection of a field from the data source of the pivot table (for example, Date)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Seleção de um campo da fonte de dados da tabela dinâmica (por exemplo, (Data)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Each result is added to the sum of the results for preceding items in the base field, in the base field’s sort order, and the total sum is shown.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Cada resultado é adicionado à soma dos resultados dos itens anteriores no campo base, na ordenação do campo base, e a soma total é mostrada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Results are always summed, even if a different summary function was used to get each result.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os resultados são sempre somados, mesmo se uma função de resumo diferente for usada para obter cada resultado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>% of row</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>% da linha</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The result is a percentage of the value of the whole row (for example, the row sum).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resultado é uma porcentagem do valor de toda a linha (por exemplo, a soma da linha).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>% of column</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>% da coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The result is a percentage of the total column value (for example, the column sum).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resultado é uma porcentagem do valor total da coluna (por exemplo, a soma da coluna).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>% of total</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>% do total</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The result is a percentage of the overall result (for example, the total sum).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resultado é uma porcentagem do resultado geral (por exemplo, a soma total).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Index</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Índice</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>(Default result x total result) / (row total x column total)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>(Resultado padrão x resultado total) / (total da linha x total da coluna)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 10: Original pivot table (top) and a Difference from example (bottom)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 10: Tabela dinâmica original (topo) e um exemplo Diferença de (embaixo)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 11: Example of a % of analysis</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 11: Exemplo de uma análise % de</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 12: Example of % difference from analysis</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 12: Exemplo de análise % diferença de</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>column and row field options</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>opções para campos de linha e coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>caixa de diálogo Tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Options for row and column fields</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Opções para campos de linha e coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Double-click a field in the Row or Column Fields areas of the Pivot Table Layout dialog to access the Data Field dialog shown in Figure 13.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique duas vezes em um campo nas áreas Linha ou Campos de coluna da caixa diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica para acessar a caixa de diálogo Campo de dados mostrado na 13.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the Data Field dialog for a row or column field, you can choose to show subtotals for each category.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na caixa de diálogo Campo de dados para um campo de linha ou coluna, pode-se escolher mostrar os subtotais para cada categoria.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Subtotals are deactivated by default.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os subtotais são desativados por padrão.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Subtotals are useful only if the values in one row or column field can be divided into subtotals for another (sub)field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os subtotais são úteis apenas se os valores em um campo de linha ou coluna puderem ser divididos em subtotais para outro (sub) campo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 13: Data Field dialog for a row or column field</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 13: Caixa de diálogo Campo de dados para um campo de linha ou coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Some examples are shown in Figures 14, 15, and 16.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Alguns exemplos são mostrados nas Figuras 14, 15e 16.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 14: No subdivision with only one row or column field</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 14: Sem subdivisão com apenas um campo de linha ou coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 15: Division of the regions for employees (two row fields) without subtotals</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 15: Divisão das regiões para funcionários (campos de duas linhas) sem subtotais</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 16: Division of the regions for employees with subtotals (by region)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 16: Divisão das regiões para funcionários com subtotais (por região)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To calculate subtotals that can also be used for the data fields (see above), select the Automatic option in the Subtotals section of the Data Field dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para calcular subtotais que também podem ser usados para os campos de dados (veja acima), selecione a opção Automático na seção Subtotais da caixa de diálogo Campo de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can choose the type of subtotal to use by selecting User-defined and then clicking the type of subtotal you want to calculate from the list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se escolher o tipo de subtotal a ser usado selecionando Definido pelo usuário e, em seguida, clicando no tipo de subtotal que deseja calcular na lista.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Functions in this list are only available when User-defined is selected.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As funções nesta lista estão disponíveis apenas quando Definido pelo usuário é selecionado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Normally, the pivot table does not show a row or column for categories that have no entries in the underlying database.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Normalmente, a tabela dinâmica não mostra uma linha ou coluna para categorias que não possuem entradas no banco de dados subjacente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>By choosing the Show items without data option, you can force these to be displayed.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ao escolher a opção Mostrar itens sem dados, pode-se forçar a exibição deles.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For illustration purposes, the data was manipulated in such a way that the employee Brigitte has no sales values for the Golf category.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para fins ilustrativos, os dados foram manipulados de forma que a funcionária Brigite não possua valores de venda para a categoria Golfe.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 17: Default setting</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 17: Configuração padrão</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 18: Setting Show items without data</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 18: Configuração Mostrar itens sem dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click the Options button on the Data Field dialog to access the Data Field Options dialog (Figure 19). Use this dialog to specify additional options for fields in the Column and Row Fields areas of the Pivot Table Layout dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique no botão Opções na caixa de diálogo Campo de dados para acessar a caixa de diálogo Opções de campo de dados (19) Use esta caixa de diálogo para especificar opções adicionais para campos nas áreas Coluna e Campos de linha da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The following options are provided:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As seguintes opções são fornecidas:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Sort by. Select the data field that you want to sort columns or rows by.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordenar por – Selecione o campo de dados pelo qual deseja classificar as colunas ou linhas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Ascending sorts the values from the lowest value to the highest value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Crescente classifica os valores do valor mais baixo para o valor mais alto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the selected field is the field for which the dialog was opened, the items are sorted by name.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se o campo selecionado for o campo para o qual a caixa de diálogo foi aberta, os itens serão classificados por nome.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If a data field was selected, the items are sorted by the resultant value of the selected data field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se um campo de dados foi selecionado, os itens são classificados pelo valor resultante do campo de dados selecionado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Similarly Descending sorts the values descending from the highest value to the lowest value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Similarmente Decrescente classifica os valores decrescentes do valor mais alto para o valor mais baixo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Manual sorts values alphabetically.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Manual classifica os valores em ordem alfabética.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Display Options.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Opções de exibição.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can specify the display options for all row fields except for the last, innermost row field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se especificar as opções de exibição para todos os campos de linha, exceto para o último campo de linha mais interno.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select from the Layout drop-down list to select the layout mode for the field in the list box.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione a partir da lista suspensa Leiaute para selecionar o modo de leiaute para o campo na caixa de listagem.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select the Empty line after each item option to add an empty row after the data for each item in the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione a opção Linha vazia após cada item de adicionar uma linha vazia após os dados de cada item na tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select or deselect the Repeat item labels option as required.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione ou desmarque a opção Repetir rótulos de itens conforme necessário.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Show Automatically.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Mostrar automaticamente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This feature displays the top or bottom nn items when you sort by a specified field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Este recurso exibe a parte superior ou inferior nn itens quando se classifica por um campo especificado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click the Show option to turn on the automatic show feature and enter the maximum number of items that you want to show automatically.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique na opção Mostrar para ativar o recurso de exibição automática e inserir o número máximo de itens que se deseja mostrar automaticamente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The From drop-down list selects to show the top or bottom items in the specified sort order.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A lista suspensa De seleciona para mostrar os itens superiores ou inferiores na ordenação especificada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Using field drop-down list selects the data field by which to sort the data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A lista suspensa Usando o campo seleciona o campo de dados pelo qual classificar os dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Hide Items.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ocultar itens.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Use these options to select the items to hide from the calculations.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Use essas opções para selecionar os itens a serem ocultados dos cálculos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Hierarchy.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Hierarquia.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select the hierarchy to use, when the field has multiple hierarchies.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione a hierarquia a ser usada, quando o campo tem várias hierarquias.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table must be based on external source data that contains data hierarchies.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A tabela dinâmica deve ser baseada em dados de origem externa que contêm hierarquias de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For the majority of users, Calc does not provide multiple hierarchies for a single field and so this option is normally grayed.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para a maioria dos usuários, o Calc não fornece várias hierarquias para um único campo e, portanto, essa opção normalmente está esmaecida.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you use a pivot table data source extension, that extension could define multiple hierarchies for some fields and then the option could become available.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>E se usar uma extensão de fonte de dados de tabela dinâmica, essa extensão pode definir várias hierarquias para alguns campos e, em seguida, a opção pode se tornar disponível.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>See the documentation supplied with that extension for more details.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Consulte a documentação fornecida com essa extensão para obter mais detalhes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 19: Data Field Options dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 19: Caixa de diálogo Opções de campo de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>filter field options</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>opções para campos de filtro</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Layout dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>caixa de diálogo Tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Options for filter fields</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Opções para campos de filtro</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Data Field dialog for fields in the Filters area is the same as for fields in the Row and Column Fields areas, even though it appears to be useless to have the same settings as described for the row and column fields.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A caixa de diálogo Campo de dados para campos na área Filtros é o mesmo que para campos no Linha e Campos de coluna áreas, embora pareça inútil ter as mesmas configurações descritas para os campos de linha e coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>With the flexibility of the pivot table, you can switch the different fields between filters, columns, or rows.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com a flexibilidade da tabela dinâmica, pode-se alternar os diferentes campos entre filtros, colunas ou linhas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The fields keep the settings that you gave them.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os campos mantêm as configurações que se deu a eles.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The filter field has the same properties as a row or column field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O campo de filtro possui as mesmas propriedades de um campo de linha ou coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>These settings only take effect when you use the field not as a filter field but as a row or column field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Essas configurações só têm efeito quando se usa o campo não como um campo de filtro, mas como um campo de linha ou coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Working with the results of the pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Trabalhar com os resultados da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Pivot Table Layout dialog is very flexible and a pivot table can be totally restructured with only a few mouse clicks.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica é muito flexível e uma tabela dinâmica pode ser totalmente reestruturada com apenas alguns cliques do mouse.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>changing layout</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>mudando o leiaute</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Changing the layout</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Mudar o Leiaute</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The layout of the pivot table can be changed quickly and easily by using drag-and-drop.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Leiaute da tabela dinâmica pode ser alterado de forma rápida e fácil usando arrastar e soltar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>With the Pivot Table Layout dialog open, fields can be dragged around from Row Fields, Column Fields, Filters, and Data Fields areas to any position you want to put them, and then dropped.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com a caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica aberta, os campos podem ser arrastados das áreas Campos de linha, Campos de coluna, Filtros, e Campos de dados para qualquer posição que se deseja colocá-los e, em seguida, soltar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Unused fields can also be added, and fields removed in error can be replaced by dragging and dropping them into the positions required.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os campos não utilizados também podem ser adicionados e os campos removidos por engano podem ser substituídos arrastando-os e soltando-os nas posições necessárias.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Some manipulation can also be carried out in the results view of the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Alguma manipulação também pode ser realizada na exibição de resultados da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Within the results of the pivot table, drag one of the filter, column, or row fields to a different position.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nos resultados da tabela dinâmica, arraste um dos campos de filtro, coluna ou linha para uma posição diferente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The cursor will change shape from its starting shape (horizontal or vertical block on the arrow head) to the opposite if moving to a different field, such as from row to column, where it can be dropped.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O cursor mudará de sua forma inicial (bloco horizontal ou vertical na ponta da seta) para o oposto se for movido para um campo diferente, como de linha para coluna, onde pode ser solto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 20: Drag a column field - note the cursor shape</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 20: Arraste um campo de coluna - observe a forma do cursor</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 21: Result of dragging column field (see Figure 20)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 21: Resultado de arrastar o campo da coluna (ver 20)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 22: Drag a row field - note the cursor shape</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 22: Arraste um campo de linha - observe a forma do cursor</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can remove a column, row, or filter field from the pivot table by clicking on it and dragging it out of the table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se remover uma coluna, linha ou campo de filtro da tabela dinâmica clicando nele e arrastando-o para fora da tabela.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The cursor changes to that shown in Figure 23.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O cursor muda para o mostrado na 23.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A field removed cannot be recovered, without returning to the Pivot Table Layout dialog to replace it.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um campo removido não pode ser recuperado, sem retornar à caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica para substituí-lo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 23: Field dragged out of the pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 23: Campo arrastado para fora da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>grouping columns or rows</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>agrumamento de linha ou colunas</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Grouping rows or columns of a pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Agrupamento de linhas ou colunas de uma tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For many analyses or summaries, the categories have to be grouped.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para muitas análises ou resumos, as categorias devem ser agrupadas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can merge the results in classes.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se mesclar os resultados em classes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can only carry out grouping on an ungrouped pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Só se pode realizar o agrupamento em uma tabela dinâmica não agrupada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>After selecting the correct cell area, select Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Group on the Menu bar, or press F12 on the keyboard.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Depois de selecionar a área de célula correta, selecione Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Agrupar na barra de menus ou tecle F12.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The type of values to be grouped is what mainly determines how the grouping function works.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O tipo de valores a serem agrupados é o que determina principalmente como a função de agrupamento funciona.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You need to distinguish between scalar values, or other values, such as text, that you want grouped.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>precisa-se distinguir entre valores escalares ou outros valores, como texto, que deseja agrupar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Before you can group, you have to produce a pivot table with ungrouped data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Antes de agrupar, deve-se produzir uma tabela dinâmica com dados desagrupados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The time needed for creating a pivot table depends mostly on the number of columns and rows and not on the size of the basic data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O tempo necessário para criar uma tabela dinâmica depende principalmente do número de colunas e linhas e não do tamanho dos dados básicos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Through grouping you can produce the pivot table with a small number of rows and columns.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por meio do agrupamento, pode-se produzir a tabela dinâmica com um pequeno número de linhas e colunas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table can contain a lot of categories, depending on your data source.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A tabela dinâmica pode conter várias categorias, dependendo da sua fonte de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To remove grouping again, click inside the group, then choose Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Ungroup, or press Ctrl+F12.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para remover o agrupamento novamente, clique dentro do grupo e escolha Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Desagrupar ou tecle Ctrl+F12.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>grouping scalar values</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>agrupamento de valores escalares</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Grouping of categories with scalar values</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Agrupamento de categorias com valores escalares</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For grouping scalar values, select a single cell in the row or column of the category to be grouped.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para agrupar valores escalares, selecione uma única célula na linha ou coluna da categoria a ser agrupada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Choose Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Group on the Menu bar or press F12 on the keyboard; Calc displays the Grouping dialog shown in Figure 24.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Escolher Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Agrupar na barra de menus ou tecle F12; O Calc exibe a caixa de diálogo Agrupar mostrada na Figura 24.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can define in which value range (Start / End) the grouping should take place.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se definir em qual faixa de valor (Início / Fim), o agrupamento deve ocorrer.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The default setting is the whole range, from the smallest to the largest value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A configuração padrão é todo o intervalo, do menor ao maior valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the field Group by, you can enter the class size, also known as the interval size.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No campo Agrupar por, pode-se inserir o tamanho da classe, também conhecido como tamanho do intervalo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 24: Grouping dialog with scalar categories</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 24: caixa de diálogo Agrupar com categorias escalares</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 25shows part of a pivot table created from a list containing speed measurements as a function of time.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A 25mostra parte de uma tabela dinâmica criada a partir de uma lista contendo medições de velocidade em função do tempo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This pivot table shows the count of km/h speed measurements in the raw data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esta tabela dinâmica mostra a contagem de medições de velocidade em km/h nos dados brutos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table in Figure 26is based on the same raw data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A tabela dinâmica na 26é baseado nos mesmos dados brutos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>However in this case the speed measurements are grouped into intervals if 10 km/h.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No entanto, neste caso, as medições de velocidade são agrupadas em intervalos de 10 km/h.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 25: Pivot table without grouping</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 25: Tabela dinâmica sem agrupamento</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 26: Pivot table with grouping</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 26: Tabela dinâmica com agrupamento</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>grouping date / time values</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>agrumapmanto de categorias data / hora</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Grouping of categories with date / time values</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Agrupamento de categorias com valores de data / hora</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For grouping date / time values, select a single cell in the row or column of the category to be grouped.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para agrupar valores de data / hora, selecione uma única célula na linha ou coluna da categoria a ser agrupada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Choose Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Group on the Menu bar or press F12 on the keyboard; Calc displays the Grouping dialog shown in Figure 27.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Escolher Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Agrupar na barra de menus ou tecle F12; O Calc exibe a caixa de diálogo Agrupar mostrada na 27.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 27: Grouping dialog for date/time categories</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 27: Caixa de diálogo Agrupar para categorias de data / hora</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can define in which value range (Start / End) the grouping should take place.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se definir em qual faixa de valor (Início / Fim), o agrupamento deve ocorrer.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The default setting is the whole range, from the smallest to the largest value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A configuração padrão é todo o intervalo, do menor ao maior valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the field Group by, you can enter the class size, also known as the interval size.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No campo Agrupar por, pode-se inserir o tamanho da classe, também conhecido como tamanho do intervalo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this case you can select one of the predefined time intervals (Seconds, Minutes, Hours, Days, Months, Quarters, or Years) as an alternative to explicitly specifying a time interval in days.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Neste caso, pode-se selecionar um dos intervalos de tempo predefinidos (Segundos, Minutos, Horas, Dias, Meses, Trimestres ou Anos) como uma alternativa para especificar explicitamente um intervalo de tempo em dias.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 28shows a pivot table configured to show the daily sales in the North region.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A 28mostra uma tabela dinâmica configurada para mostrar as vendas diárias na região Norte.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 28: Pivot table without grouping</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 28: Tabela dinâmica sem agrupamento</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 29shows the same data but configured to show the monthly sales in the North region.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A 29mostra os mesmos dados, mas configurado para mostrar as vendas mensais na região Norte.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 29: Pivot table with grouping</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 29: Tabela dinâmica com agrupamento</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>grouping without intervals</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>agrupamento sem intervalos</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Grouping without automatic creation of intervals</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Agrupamento sem criação automática de intervalos</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>It is not possible to create intervals for some categories (for example, those containing text fields).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Não é possível criar intervalos para algumas categorias (por exemplo, aquelas que contêm campos de texto).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>However, for such fields it is possible to define which values are put together in one group.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No entanto, para tais campos é possível definir quais valores são colocados juntos em um grupo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For grouping of these categories, select in the results of the pivot table all the individual field values that you want to put together in the group.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para agrupar essas categorias, selecione nos resultados da tabela dinâmica todos os valores de campo individuais que deseja reunir no grupo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>With more than one cell selected, choose Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Group on the Menu bar, or press F12 on the keyboard, to group the selected cells.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com mais de uma célula selecionada, escolha Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Agrupar na barra de menus ou tecle F12, para agrupar as células selecionadas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Tip</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Dica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can select several non-contiguous cells by pressing and holding the Control key while clicking with the mouse.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se selecionar várias células não contíguas pressionando e segurando a tecla Ctrl enquanto clica com o mouse.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Given the input data shown in Figure 30, create a pivot table with Department in the Row Fields area and Sum - Sick days in the Data Fields area.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Com os dados de entrada mostrados na 30, crie uma tabela dinâmica com Departamento na área Campos de linha e soma – dias de atestado médico na área Campos de Dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The result should be as shown in Figure 31.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resultado deve ser conforme mostrado na 31.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 30: Database with text categories</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 30: Banco de dados com categorias de texto</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 31: Pivot table with text categories</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 31: Tabela dinâmica com categorias de texto</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the results of the pivot table select Accounting, Purchasing, and Sales in the Department column.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nos resultados da tabela dinâmica, selecione Contabilidade, Compras e Vendas na coluna Departamento.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Group on the Menu bar or press F12 on the keyboard.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Agrupar na barra de menus ou tecle F12.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table result updates to reflect the new group, as shown in Figure 32.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O resultado da tabela dinâmica é atualizado para refletir o novo grupo, conforme mostrado na 32.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 32: Summary of single categories in one group</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 32: Resumo de categorias individuais em um grupo</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the updated pivot table result, select Assembly, Production, and Warehouse in the Department column.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No resultado atualizado da tabela dinâmica, selecione Montagem, Produção e Armazém na coluna Departamento.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Group on the Menu bar or press F12 on the keyboard.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Agrupar na barra de menus ou tecle F12.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table updates again to reflect the new group, as shown in Figure 33.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A tabela dinâmica é atualizada novamente para refletir o novo grupo, conforme mostrado na 33.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can change the default names for the groups and the newly created group field by editing the name in the input field (for example changing Group2 to Technical).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se alterar os nomes padrão para os grupos e o campo de grupo recém-criado editando o nome no campo de entrada (por exemplo, alterando Grupo2 para Técnico).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table will remember these settings, even if you change the layout later on.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A tabela dinâmica se lembrará dessas configurações, mesmo se alterar o leiaute posteriormente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 33: Grouping finished</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 33: Agrupamento concluído</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To add partial sums for the groups, right-click the results of the pivot table and select the Properties option.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para adicionar somas parciais para os grupos, clique com o botão direito nos resultados da tabela dinâmica e selecione a opção Propriedades.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Double-click the Department2 entry in the Row Fields area and select the Automatic option on the Data Field dialog (Figure 13). Click the two OK buttons and the pivot table is updated to include the partial sums for the groups, as shown in Figure 34.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique duas vezes na entrada Departamento2 na área Campos de linha e selecione a opção Automático na caixa de diálogo Campo de dados (13) Clique no botão OK e a tabela dinâmica é atualizada para incluir as somas parciais dos grupos, conforme mostrado na 34.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 34: Renamed group and partial results</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 34: Grupo renomeado e resultados parciais</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If it is not enabled already, select the Enable drill to details option on the Pivot Table Layout dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se ainda não estiver habilitado, selecione a opção Ativar análise de dados na caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Double-click the Group 1 and Technical entries in the Department2 column to collapse/expand the group entries (for example, Figure 35shows both groups collapsed).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique duas vezes nas entradas Grupo1 e Grupo2 na coluna Departamento2 para recolher / expandir as entradas do grupo (por exemplo, a 35mostra os dois grupos recolhidos).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 35: Reduced to the new groups</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 35: Reduzido para os novos grupos</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A well-structured database makes manual sorting within the pivot table obsolete.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um banco de dados bem estruturado torna obsoleta a ordenação manual na tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the example shown, you could add another column with the name Department, that has the correct entry for each person based on whether the employee’s department belongs to the group Office or Technical.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No exemplo mostrado, poderia adicionar outra coluna com o nome Departamento, que tem a entrada correta para cada pessoa dependendo se o departamento do funcionário pertence ao grupo Escritório ou Técnico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The mapping for this (1:n relationship) can be done easily with the VLOOKUP() function.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O mapeamento para isso (relacionamento 1: n) pode ser feito facilmente com a função PROCV().</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>sorting results</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>classificando o resultado</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Sorting the result</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordenar o resultado</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The results of a pivot table are by default sorted so that categories in columns and rows are presented in ascending order.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os resultados de uma tabela dinâmica são, por padrão, ordenados de forma que as categorias nas colunas e linhas sejam apresentadas em ordem crescente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>There are three ways to change the sorting order:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Existem três maneiras de alterar a ordenação:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select a sort order from the drop-down menu on a column’s heading.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecionar uma ordenação no menu suspenso no título de uma coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Sort manually by using drag and drop.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordenar manualmente usando arrastar e soltar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select a sort order through the Data Field Options dialog for the appropriate row or column field (Figure 19).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecione uma ordenação através da caixa de diálogo Opções de campo de dados para a linha apropriada ou campo de coluna (19)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Select sort order from drop-down menus on each column heading</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecionar a ordem nos menus suspensos em cada título de coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The simplest way to sort entries is to click the arrow on the right side of the column heading for a row or column field, and select one of the three sorting options (Figure 36):</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A maneira mais simples de ordenar as entradas é clicar na seta à direita do título da coluna de um campo de linha ou coluna e selecionar uma das três opções de ordenação (36):</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Sort Ascending</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordem crescente</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Sort Descending</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordem decrescente</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Custom Sort</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordem personalizada</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 36: Column sorting and filtering dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 36: caixa de diálogo de ordenação e filtragem de colunas</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Selecting the Custom Sort option sorts according to one of the predefined custom sorts defined in Tools &gt; Options &gt; LibreOffice Calc &gt; Sort Lists.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Selecionando a opção Ordenação personalizada ordena de acordo com uma das ordenações personalizadas predefinidas definidas em Ferramentas &gt; Opções &gt; LibreOffice Calc &gt; Listas ordenadas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>See Chapter 2, Entering, Editing, and Formatting Data for more information about creating and using sort lists.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Consulte o Capítulo 2, Inserir, editar e formatar dados para obter mais informações sobre como criar e usar listas de ordenação.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This dialog also provides facilities for simple filtering of the data in the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esta caixa de diálogo também fornece recursos para filtragem simples dos dados na tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Check the required individual boxes to select the data displayed in the results of the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Marque as caixas individuais necessárias para selecionar os dados exibidos nos resultados da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Options are provided to show all, show only the current item, or hide only the current item.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As opções são fornecidas para mostrar tudo, mostrar apenas o item atual ou ocultar apenas o item atual.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click OK to activate the selected filtering.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique em OK para ativar a filtragem selecionada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Once filtering has been carried out, the color of the arrow changes from black to blue, and a small square of matching color is added to the bottom right of the arrow button (Figure 37).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Uma vez que a filtragem foi realizada, a cor da seta muda de preto para azul, e um pequeno quadrado de cor correspondente é adicionado ao canto inferior direito do botão de seta (37)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 37: Arrow color change and indicator square on column heading</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 37: Mudança de cor da seta e quadrado do indicador no cabeçalho da coluna</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Sort manually by using drag and drop</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordenar manualmente usando arrastar e soltar</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can change the order within the categories by moving the cells with the category values in the results of the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se alterar a ordem dentro das categorias movendo as células com os valores das categorias nos resultados da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The dragged cell is inserted above the cell on which you drop it.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A célula arrastada é inserida acima da célula em que se a soltou.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Be aware that in Calc, a cell must be selected, it is not enough that the cursor is in the cell.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esteja ciente de que no Calc, uma célula deve ser selecionada, não basta que o cursor esteja na célula.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The background of a selected cell is marked with a different color.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O plano de fundo de uma célula selecionada é marcado com uma cor diferente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To mark a single cell do one of the following:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para marcar uma única célula, siga um destes procedimentos:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click, then Shift+click the cell.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique, a seguir Shift+clique na célula.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Press the mouse button, drag a range across two cells, do not release the mouse button, and then drag back to the first cell.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pressione o botão do mouse, arraste um intervalo entre duas células, não solte o botão do mouse e arraste de volta para a primeira célula.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Release the mouse button.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Solte o botão do mouse.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can now move the individual cell by drag and drop.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Agora pode-se mover a célula individual arrastando e soltando.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To select several cells, mark one cell with no extra key pressed, then press the Shift or Ctrl key while clicking in other cells.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para selecionar várias células, marque uma célula sem nenhuma tecla sendo pressionada e pressione a tecla Shift ou Ctrl enquanto clica em outras células.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Sort automatically</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ordenar automaticamente</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To sort automatically, right-click within the pivot table and choose Properties.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para classificar automaticamente, clique com o botão direito na tabela dinâmica e selecione Propriedades.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This will open the Pivot Table Layout dialog (Figure 2). Double-click the row or column field you want to sort.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Isso abrirá a caixa de diálogo Leiaute da Tabela Dinâmica (2) Clique duas vezes no campo de linha ou coluna que deseja classificar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the Data Field dialog which opens (Figure 13), click Options to display the Data Field Options dialog (Figure 19).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na caixa de diálogo Campo de dados que é aberta (13), clique Opções para exibir a caixa de diálogo Opções de Campo de Dados (19)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For Sort by, choose either Ascending, Descending, or Manual.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para Ordenar por, escolha qualquer um Crescente, Decrescente ou Manual.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the selected field is the field for which the dialog was opened, the items are sorted by name.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se o campo selecionado for o campo para o qual a caixa de diálogo foi aberta, os itens serão classificados por nome.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If a data field was selected, the items are sorted by the resultant value of the selected data field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se um campo de dados foi selecionado, os itens são classificados pelo valor resultante do campo de dados selecionado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Ascending sorts the values from the lowest value to the highest value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Crescente classifica os valores do valor mais baixo para o valor mais alto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Similarly Descending sorts the values descending from the highest value to the lowest value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Similarmente Decrescente classifica os valores decrescentes do valor mais alto para o valor mais baixo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Manual sorts values alphabetically.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Manual classifica os valores em ordem alfabética.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>showing details (drilling)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>mostrando detalhes (drilling)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Drilling (showing details)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Detalhar (mostrar os detalhes)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Use drilling to show the related detailed data for a single, compressed value in the pivot table result.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Use o detalhamento para mostrar os dados detalhados relacionados para um único valor compactado no resultado da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This facility is available only if you selected the Enable drill to details option on the Pivot Table Layout dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Este recurso está disponível apenas se se selecionou a opção Ativar análise de dados na caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To activate a drill, double-click on the cell or choose Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Show Details.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para ativar um detalhamento, clique duas vezes na célula ou escolha Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Mostrar detalhes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>There are two possibilities:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Há duas possibilidades.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The active cell is a row or column field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A célula ativa é um campo de linha ou coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this case, drill means an additional breakdown into the categories of another field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nesse caso, o detalhamento significa uma divisão adicional nas categorias de outro campo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For example, double-click on the cell with the value Golf.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por exemplo, clique duas vezes na célula com o valor Golfe.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this instance the values that are aggregated within Golf can be subdivided using another field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Neste caso, os valores que são agregados em Golfe podem ser subdivididos usando outro campo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 38: Before the drill down for Golf</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 38: Antes do exercício de golfe</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Show Detail dialog appears allowing you to select the field to use for further subdivision.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A caixa de diálogo Mostrar detalhes aparece permitindo que se selecione o campo a ser usado para subdivisão posterior.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this example, Employee.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Neste exemplo, Funcionário.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 39: Selecting the field for the subdivision</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 39: Selecionando o campo para a subdivisão</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 40: After the drill down</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 40: Após o detalhamento</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To hide the details again, double-click on the cell Golf or choose Data &gt; Group and Outline &gt; Hide Details.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para ocultar novamente os detalhes, clique duas vezes na célula Golfe ou selecione Dados &gt; Esquema &gt; Ocultar detalhes na barra de menu</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table remembers your selection (in our example the field Employee) by adding and hiding the selected field, so that for the next drill down for a field in the Category column the dialog does not appear.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A tabela dinâmica lembra sua seleção (em nosso exemplo o campo Funcionário) adicionando e ocultando o campo selecionado, de modo que para o próximo detalhamento de um campo na coluna Categoria a caixa de diálogo não aparece.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To remove the selection Employee, open the Pivot Table Layout dialog and delete the unwanted selection in the Row or Column Fields area.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para remover a seleção Funcionário, abra a caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica e exclua a seleção indesejada na área Campo de Linha ou Campos de coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The active cell is a data field.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A célula ativa é um campo de dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In this case, drill down results in a listing of all data entries of the data source that aggregate to this value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nesse caso, o detalhamento resulta em uma lista de todas as entradas de dados da fonte que agregam a esse valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In our example, if we double-click on the cell with the value $18,741 from Figure 38, we would have a new list of all data sets that are included in this value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Em nosso exemplo, se clicarmos duas vezes na célula com o valor R$ 18.741,00 da 38, teríamos uma nova lista de todos os conjuntos de dados incluídos neste valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This list is displayed in a new sheet.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esta lista é exibida em uma nova planilha.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 41: New sheet after the drill down for a value in a data field</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 41: Nova planilha após o detalhamento de um valor em um campo de dados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>filtering</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>filtragem</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Filtering</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Filtragem</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To limit the pivot table analysis to a subset of the information that is contained in the data basis, you can filter the pivot table results.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para limitar a análise da tabela dinâmica a um subconjunto das informações contidas na base de dados, pode-se filtrar os resultados da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>An autofilter or default filter used on the sheet containing the raw data has no effect on the pivot table analysis process.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um filtro automático ou filtro padrão usado na planilha que contém os dados brutos não tem efeito no processo de análise da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table always uses the complete list that was selected when it was started.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A tabela dinâmica sempre usa a lista completa que foi selecionada quando foi iniciada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To do this, click the Filter button at the top left above the results, or right-click in the results and select Filter in the context menu.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para fazer isso, clique no botão Filtro no canto superior esquerdo acima dos resultados, ou clique com o botão direito nos resultados e selecione Filtro no menu de contexto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Note</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Nota</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Filter button is available only if the Add filter option on the Pivot Table Layout dialog is selected.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O botão Filtro está disponível apenas se a opção Adicionar filtro na caixa de diálogo Leiaute da Tabela Dinâmica é selecionado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 42: Filter button in the upper left area of the pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 42: botão Filtro na área superior esquerda da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the Filter dialog (Figure 43), you can define up to three filter options that are used in the same way as Calc’s default filter.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na caixa de diálogo Filtro (43), pode-se definir até três opções de filtro que são usadas da mesma forma que o filtro padrão do Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The controls in the Options section of this dialog are similar to the equivalent controls on Calc’s Standard Filter dialog – see Chapter 2, Entering, Editing, and Formatting Data for more information.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os controles na seção Opções desta caixa de diálogo é semelhante aos controles equivalentes na caixa de diálogo Filtro padrão do Calc – consulte o Capítulo 2, Inserir, Editar e Formatar Dados para obter mais informações.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 43: Dialog for defining the filter</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 43: Caixa de diálogo para definir o filtro</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The data presented in a pivot table can also be filtered using the drop-downs on the right hand side of column headings or by using filter fields.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os dados apresentados em uma tabela dinâmica também podem ser filtrados usando os menus suspensos no lado direito dos cabeçalhos das colunas ou usando campos de filtro.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Filtering through column headings is described in “Select sort order from drop-down menus on each column heading” on page 22.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A filtragem pelos cabeçalhos das colunas é descrita em “Selecionar a ordem nos menus suspensos em cada título de coluna” acima.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Filter fields (that is, fields that you placed in the Filters area of the Pivot Table Layout dialog) are another practical way to filter the results of the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Campos de filtro (ou seja, campos que se colocou na área Filtros da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica) são outra maneira prática de filtrar os resultados da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The advantage is that the filtering criteria used are clearly visible.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A vantagem é que os critérios de filtragem usados são claramente visíveis.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click the arrow on the right side of the filter field button to access the associated filtering dialog (Figure 44).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique na seta do lado direito do botão do campo de filtro para acessar a caixa de diálogo de filtragem associada (44)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 44: Filter field filtering dialog</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 44: Caixa de diálogo de filtragem de campo de filtro</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The text adjacent to a filter field button indicates the filtering status, that is “- all -” when nothing is filtered, “- multiple -” when multiple but not all items are filtered, or the value when only that value is not filtered.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O texto adjacente a um botão do campo de filtro indica o status da filtragem, ou seja, “- todos -” quando nada é filtrado, “- vários -” quando vários, mas nem todos os itens são filtrados, ou o valor quando apenas esse valor não é filtrado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>refreshing / updating changed values</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>atualizando valores alterados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot tables</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Updating (refreshing) changed values</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Atualizar os valores alterados</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>After you have created the pivot table, changes in the source data do not cause an automatic update in the resulting table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Depois de criar a tabela dinâmica, as alterações nos dados de origem não causam uma atualização automática na tabela resultante.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You must update (refresh) the pivot table manually after changing any of the underlying data values.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Deve-se atualizar (atualizar) a tabela dinâmica manualmente após alterar qualquer um dos valores de dados subjacentes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Changes in the source data could appear in two ways:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As alterações nos dados de origem podem aparecer de duas maneiras:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The content of existing data sets has been changed.For example, you might have changed a sales value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O conteúdo dos conjuntos de dados existentes foi alterado. Por exemplo, pode-se ter alterado um valor de venda.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To update the pivot table, left-click in the results area and choose Data &gt; Pivot Table &gt; Refresh on the Menu bar, or right-click in the results area and choose Refresh in the context menu.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para atualizar a tabela dinâmica, clique com o botão esquerdo nos resultados área e escolha Dados &gt; Tabela dinâmica &gt; Atualizar na barra de menu, ou clique com o botão direito no resultado área e escolha Atualizar no menu de contexto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You have added or deleted data sets in the original list.In this case the change means that the pivot table has to use a different area of the spreadsheet for its analysis.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Adicionou-se ou excluiu-se conjuntos de dados na lista original. Nesse caso, a mudança significa que a tabela dinâmica deve usar uma área diferente da planilha para sua análise.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If a simple addition to the list was made (for example, a new sale from a different employee was inserted), it is possible to update the pivot table by changing the range in the Selection field in the Source area of the Pivot Table Layout dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se uma simples adição à lista foi feita (por exemplo, uma nova venda de um funcionário diferente foi inserida), isto é possível atualizar a tabela dinâmica alterando o intervalo no campo Seleção na área Fonte da caixa de diálogo Leiaute da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Fundamental changes to the data set collection means you must redo the pivot table from the beginning.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Mudanças fundamentais na coleta do conjunto de dados significam que deve-se refazer a tabela dinâmica desde o início.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Cell formatting</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Formatação de célula:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The cells in the results area of the pivot table are automatically formatted by Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As células na área de resultados da tabela dinâmica são formatadas automaticamente pelo Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can change this formatting using all the tools in Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se alterar essa formatação usando todas as ferramentas do Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>However if you make any change in the design of the pivot table using direct formatting, the formatting will return to that applied automatically by Calc when the table is next refreshed.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No entanto, se fizer qualquer alteração no design da tabela dinâmica usando formatação direta, a formatação retornará àquela aplicada automaticamente pelo Calc na próxima atualização da tabela.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>On creating a pivot table, six standard cell styles are added to the list of styles in the document if they are not included already.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ao criar uma tabela dinâmica, seis estilos de célula padrão são adicionados à lista de estilos no documento, se ainda não estiverem incluídos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Each of these styles is applied to part of the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Cada um desses estilos é aplicado a parte da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can customize these pivot table styles.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se personalizar esses estilos de tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The pivot table styles are:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os estilos da tabela dinâmica são:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Category</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Categoria da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Corner</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Canto da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Field</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Campo da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Result</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Resultado da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Title</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Título da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot Table Value</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Valor da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Use the pivot table styles to make sure that the format of your pivot table is not unexpectedly changed during updates and that all pivot tables in your document have the same appearance.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Use os estilos de tabela dinâmica para garantir que o formato de sua tabela dinâmica não seja alterado inesperadamente durante as atualizações e que todas as tabelas dinâmicas em seu documento tenham a mesma aparência.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For the number format in the data field, Calc uses the number format that is used in the corresponding cell in the source list.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para o formato de número no campo de dados, o Calc usa o formato de número que é usado na célula correspondente na lista de origem.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In most cases, this is useful (for example, if the values are in the currency format, then the corresponding cell in the result area is also formatted as currency).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na maioria dos casos, isso é útil (por exemplo, se os valores estiverem no formato de moeda, a célula correspondente na área de resultados também será formatada como moeda).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>However, if the result is a fraction or a percentage, the pivot table does not recognize that this might be a problem; such results must either be without a unit or be displayed as a percentage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No entanto, se o resultado for uma fração ou porcentagem, a tabela dinâmica não reconhece que isso pode ser um problema; esses resultados devem ser sem unidade ou exibidos como uma porcentagem.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Although you can correct the number format manually, the correction stays in effect only until the next update.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Embora possa-se corrigir o formato do número manualmente, a correção permanece em vigor apenas até a próxima atualização.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Deleting a pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Excluir uma tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To delete a pivot table, left-click in any cell of the pivot table and select Data &gt; Pivot Table &gt; Delete on the Menu bar, or right-click in any cell of the pivot table and select Delete in the context menu.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para excluir uma tabela dinâmica, clique com o botão esquerdo em qualquer célula da tabela dinâmica e selecionar Dados &gt; Tabela dinâmica &gt; Excluir na barra de menu, ou clique com o botão direito em qualquer célula da tabela dinâmica e selecione Excluir no menu de contexto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Caution</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Cuidado</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you delete a pivot table with an associated pivot chart, the pivot chart is also deleted.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se excluir uma tabela dinâmica com um gráfico dinâmico associado, o gráfico dinâmico também será excluído.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc opens a dialog box to confirm the pivot chart deletion.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Calc abre uma caixa de diálogo para confirmar a exclusão do gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>GETPIVOTDATA function</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>função INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Using pivot table results elsewhere</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Utilizar os resultados da tabela dinâmica em outro lugar</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The problem</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O problema</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Normally, you create a reference to a value by entering the address of the cell that contains the value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Normalmente, cria-se uma referência a um valor inserindo o endereço da célula que contém o valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For example, the formula =C6*2 creates a reference to cell C6 and returns the doubled value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por exemplo, a fórmula =C6*2 cria uma referência à célula C6 e retorna o valor dobrado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If this cell is located in the results area of the pivot table, it contains the result that was calculated by referencing specific categories of the row and column fields.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se esta célula estiver localizada na área de resultados da tabela dinâmica, ela conterá o resultado que foi calculado referenciando categorias específicas dos campos de linha e coluna.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In Figure 45, the cell C6 contains the sum of the sales values of the employee Hans in the category Sailing.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Na 46, a célula C6 contém a soma dos valores de vendas do funcionário Carlos na categoria Tênis.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The formula in the cell C12 uses this value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A fórmula na célula C12 usa esse valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 45: Formula reference to a cell of the pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 46: Referência de fórmula a uma célula da tabela dinâmica</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the underlying data or the layout of the pivot table changes, then you must take into account that the sales value for Hans in the Sailing category might appear in a different cell.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se os dados subjacentes ou o Leiaute da tabela dinâmica mudarem, deve-se levar em consideração que o valor de venda de Carlos na categoria Tênis pode aparecer em uma célula diferente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Your formula still references the cell C6 and therefore uses a wrong value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Sua fórmula ainda faz referência à célula C6 e, portanto, usa um valor errado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The correct value is in a different location.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O valor correto está em um local diferente.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For example, in Figure 46, the location is now C7.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por exemplo, na 47, o local correto agora é C5.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 46: The value that you really want to use can be found now in a different location</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 47: A formula agora tem a referencia errada (a tabela foi filtrada)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The solution: Function GETPIVOTDATA()</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A solução: Função INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA()</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Use the function GETPIVOTDATA() to have a reference to a value inside the pivot table by using the specific identifying categories for this value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Use a função INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA() para ter uma referência a um valor dentro da tabela dinâmica usando as categorias de identificação específicas para este valor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This function can be used with formulas in Calc if you want to reuse the results from the pivot table elsewhere in your spreadsheet.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esta função pode ser usada com fórmulas no Calc se quiser reutilizar os resultados da tabela dinâmica em outra parte da planilha de trabalho.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Syntax</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Sintaxe</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The syntax has two variations:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A sintaxe tem duas variações:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>GETPIVOTDATA(Target Field; Pivot Table[; Field 1; Item 1][; ... [Field 126; Item 126]])</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA(Campo de dados; Tabela dinâmica; Nome do campo / item1; Nome do campo / item2;...)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>or</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>ou</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>GETPIVOTDATA(Pivot Table; Constraints)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA(Tabela Dinâmica; Restrições)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The square brackets in the first variation surround optional arguments.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os colchetes na primeira variação envolvem os argumentos opcionais.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>First syntax variation</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Primeira variação de sintaxe</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The Target Field specifies which data field of the pivot table is used within the function.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Campo Alvo especifica qual campo de dados da tabela dinâmica é usado na função.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If your pivot table has only one data field, this entry is ignored, but you must enter it anyway.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se sua tabela dinâmica tiver apenas um campo de dados, esta entrada será ignorada, mas se deverá inseri-la de qualquer maneira.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If your pivot table has more than one data field, then you have to enter the field name from the underlying data source (for example “Sales Value”) or the field name of the data field itself (for example “Sum – Sales Value”).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se a sua tabela dinâmica tiver mais de um campo de dados, se deverá inserir o nome do campo da fonte de dados subjacente (por exemplo “Valor de vendas”) ou o nome do campo do próprio campo de dados (por exemplo “Soma – Valor de vendas”)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The argument Pivot Table specifies the pivot table that you want to use.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O argumento Tabela Dinâmica específica a tabela dinâmica que se deseja usar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>It is possible that your document contains more than one pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>É possível que o seu documento contenha mais de uma tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Enter here a cell reference that is inside the area of your pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Insira aqui uma referência de célula que esteja dentro da área de sua tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>It might be a good idea to always use the upper left corner cell of your pivot table, so that you can be sure that the cell will always be within your pivot table, even if the layout changes.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode ser uma boa ideia usar sempre a célula do canto superior esquerdo de sua tabela dinâmica, para ter certeza de que a célula sempre estará dentro de sua tabela dinâmica, mesmo se o Leiaute mudar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Example: GETPIVOTDATA("Sales Value",A1)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Exemplo: =INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA(“Valor de vendas”; A1)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you enter only the first two arguments, then the function returns the total result of the pivot table (“Sum – Sales Value” entered as the field, will return a value of 408,765).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se inserir apenas os dois primeiros argumentos, a função retornará o resultado total da tabela dinâmica (“Soma – Valor de vendas” inserido como o campo, retornará um valor de 408.765).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can add more arguments as pairs with Field name and Element to retrieve specific partial sums.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se adicionar mais argumentos como pares com Nome do campo e Elemento para recuperar somas parciais específicas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the example in Figure 47, where we want to get the partial sum of Hans for Sailing, the formula in cell C12 would look like this:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No exemplo da 48, onde queremos obter a soma parcial de Carlos para vela e tênis, a fórmula na célula C12 seria assim:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>=GETPIVOTDATA("Sales Value",A1,"Employee","Hans","Category","Sailing")</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>=INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA("Soma - Valor de Venda";A1;"Funcionário";"Carlos";"Categoria";"Tênis")</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 47: First syntax variation</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 48: Primeira variação de sintaxe</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Second syntax variation</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Segunda variação de sintaxe</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The argument Pivot Table has to be given in the same way as for the first syntax variation.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O argumento Tabela Dinâmica tem de ser fornecido da mesma forma que para a primeira variação de sintaxe.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>For the Constraints, enter a list separated by spaces to specify the value you want from the pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para as Restrições, insira uma lista separada por espaços para especificar o valor que se deseja da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This list must contain the name of the data field, if there is more than one data field; otherwise it is not required.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esta lista deve conter o nome do campo de dados, se houver mais de um campo de dados; caso contrário, não é necessário.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To select a specific partial result, add more entries in the form of Field name[Element].</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para selecionar um resultado parcial específico, adicione mais entradas na forma de Nome do campo [Elemento].</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the example in Figure 48, where we want to get the partial sum of Hans for Sailing, the formula in cell C12 would look like this:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No exemplo da 49, onde queremos obter a soma parcial de Carlos para Tênis, a fórmula na célula C12 seria assim:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>=GETPIVOTDATA(A1,"Sales Value Employee[Hans] Category[Sailing]")</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>=INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA(A1;"Valor de Venda [Carlos] Categoria [Tênis]")</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 48: Second syntax variation</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 49: Segunda variação de sintaxe</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>When working with data sets containing date information, you must take care if you use the date information in the GETPIVOTDATA() function.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Ao trabalhar com conjuntos de dados que contêm informações de data, você deve tomar cuidado se usar as informações de data na função INFODADOSTABELADINÂMICA().</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The function will only recognize the date entry if it is entered into the formula in exactly the same way that it appears in the data set from which the pivot table is produced.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A função só reconhecerá a entrada de data se ela for inserida na fórmula exatamente da mesma maneira que aparece no conjunto de dados a partir do qual a tabela dinâmica é produzida.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>In the example of Figure 49, an error is returned when the date format does not match that of the data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>No exemplo da 50, um erro é retornado quando o formato da data não corresponde ao dos dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Only with the correct format is the result returned.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Somente com o formato correto o resultado é retornado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 49: Error produced if date information is not entered correctly</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 50: Erro produzido se a informação da data não for inserida corretamente</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Using pivot charts</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Gráficos dinâmicos</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Introduction</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Introdução</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A pivot table is a powerful tool to reorganize, manipulate and summarize data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Uma tabela dinâmica é uma ferramenta poderosa para reorganizar, manipular e resumir dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A pivot chart provides a visual representation of the information in a pivot table.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um gráfico dinâmico fornece uma representação visual das informações em uma tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can create a pivot chart from the output of a pivot table and, if the pivot table gets changed, so does the pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Pode-se criar um gráfico dinâmico a partir da saída de uma tabela dinâmica e, se a tabela dinâmica for alterada, o gráfico dinâmico também mudará.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>differences from other charts</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>diferença de outros gráficos</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>pivot charts</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>gráficos dinâmicos</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot charts are a special case of the more general Calc charts described in Chapter 3, Creating Charts and Graphs.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os gráficos dinâmicos são um caso especial dos gráficos mais gerais do Calc descritos no Capítulo 3, Criando tabelas e gráficos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The main differences between pivot charts and other charts in Calc are as follows:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>As principais diferenças entre os gráficos dinâmicos e outros gráficos no Calc são as seguintes:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>A pivot chart tracks the changes in the data issued from a pivot table and Calc automatically adjusts the data series and data range of the pivot chart accordingly.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um gráfico dinâmico rastreia as alterações nos dados emitidos de uma tabela dinâmica e o Calc ajusta automaticamente a série de dados e o intervalo de dados do gráfico dinâmico de acordo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot chart buttons are provided on pivot charts.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os botões do gráfico dinâmico são fornecidos nos gráficos dinâmicos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>These buttons are unique to pivot charts and are not provided on Calc’s normal charts.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esses botões são exclusivos para gráficos dinâmicos e não são fornecidos nos gráficos normais do Calc.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>An important purpose of the buttons is to represent the layout of the underlying pivot table and they show the pivot table’s fields.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Um objetivo importante dos botões é representar o Leiaute da tabela dinâmica subjacente e mostrar os campos da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Buttons representing the filter fields (if present) are provided at the top of the pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os botões que representam os campos de filtro (se houver) são fornecidos na parte superior do gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Buttons representing the row fields are provided at the bottom of the pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os botões que representam os campos de linha são fornecidos na parte inferior do gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Buttons representing the column fields are stacked in the legend at the right of the pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os botões que representam os campos da coluna são empilhados na legenda à direita do gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>You can also use pivot chart buttons to filter the data displayed in the pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Você também pode usar os botões do gráfico dinâmico para filtrar os dados exibidos no gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 50: Sample pivot chart and associated pivot table</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 51: Exemplo de tabela dinâmica Figura 52: Gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Creating a pivot chart</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Criar um gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To create a pivot chart, click inside the pivot table and select Insert &gt; Chart on the Menu bar or click the Insert Chart icon on the Standard toolbar.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para criar um gráfico dinâmico, clique dentro da tabela dinâmica e selecione Inserir &gt; Gráfico na barra de menu ou clique no ícone Inserir gráfico na barra de ferramentas padrão.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc automatically detects the pivot table and opens the Chart Wizard.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Calc detecta automaticamente a tabela dinâmica e abre o Assistente de gráfico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Through the Chart Wizard you can select the chart type and chart elements for the pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Por meio do Assistente de gráfico, pode-se selecionar o tipo de gráfico e os elementos do gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The wizard is similar to the corresponding wizard for normal charts but for pivot charts, the steps to define data range and data series are disabled.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O assistente é semelhante ao assistente correspondente para gráficos normais, mas para gráficos dinâmicos, as etapas para definir o intervalo de dados e as séries de dados são desativadas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The first step in the wizard is to select the chart type and the same options are available as for a normal chart (Figure 51).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A primeira etapa do assistente é selecionar o tipo de gráfico e as mesmas opções estão disponíveis para um gráfico normal (53).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 51: Select the chart type through the Chart Wizard when creating a pivot chart</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 53: Selecione o tipo de gráfico por meio do Assistente de gráfico ao criar um gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The second step is to select the chart elements and these are similar to those for normal charts (Figure 52).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A segunda etapa é selecionar os elementos do gráfico e estes são semelhantes aos dos gráficos normais (54).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 52: Enter chart elements through the Chart Wizard when creating a pivot chart</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 54: Insira os elementos do gráfico por meio Assistente de gráfico ao criar um gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click Finish to close the wizard and create the pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique Finalizar para fechar o assistente e criar o gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Editing a pivot chart</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Editar um gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>After you have created a pivot chart, you may find that you would like to move it, change its size or improve its appearance.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Depois de criar um gráfico dinâmico, pode-se descobrir que gostaria de movê-lo, alterar seu tamanho ou melhorar sua aparência.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc provides tools for changing the chart type, chart elements, fonts, colors, and many other options.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Calc fornece ferramentas para alterar o tipo de gráfico, elementos do gráfico, fontes, cores e muitas outras opções.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The facilities provided for pivot charts are the same as those available for normal charts; see Chapter 3, Creating Charts and Graphs.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os recursos fornecidos para gráficos dinâmicos são os mesmos disponíveis para gráficos normais; consulte o Capítulo 3, Criação de tabelas e gráficos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Updating a pivot chart</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Atualizar um gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If the source data of the pivot table changes, refresh the pivot table and the pivot chart is also updated accordingly.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se os dados de origem da tabela dinâmica forem alterados, atualize a tabela dinâmica e o gráfico dinâmico também será atualizado de acordo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To refresh the pivot table (and thus the pivot chart), click in any cell within the pivot table and select Data &gt; Pivot Table &gt; Refresh on the Menu bar or select Refresh in the context menu.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para atualizar a tabela dinâmica (e, portanto, o gráfico dinâmico), clique em qualquer célula dentro a tabela dinâmica e selecione Dados &gt; Tabela Dinâmica &gt; Atualizar na barra de menu ou selecione Atualizar no menu de contexto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Filtering a pivot chart</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Filtrando um gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Use filters to remove unwanted data from a pivot chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Use filtros para remover dados indesejados de um gráfico dinâmico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>All filters applied to a pivot table affect any linked pivot chart equally, since the table and chart show exactly the same data.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Todos os filtros aplicados a uma tabela dinâmica afetam igualmente qualquer gráfico dinâmico vinculado, pois a tabela e o gráfico mostram exatamente os mesmos dados.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The various pivot table filtering mechanisms are described in “Filtering” on page 24.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os vários mecanismos de filtragem da tabela dinâmica são descritos em "Filtragem" acima.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot chart buttons include a down arrow to indicate that there is an associated pop-up action.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os botões do gráfico dinâmico incluem uma seta para baixo para indicar que há uma ação pop-up associada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If any filtering is applied, then this arrow turns from black to blue.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se qualquer filtro for aplicado, esta seta muda de preto para azul.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Pivot chart buttons become operational when you double-click on the chart and a gray frame appears around the chart.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os botões do gráfico dinâmico tornam-se operacionais quando se clica duas vezes no gráfico e um quadro cinza aparece ao redor do gráfico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>This action puts the pivot chart into edit mode.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Esta ação coloca o gráfico dinâmico no modo de edição.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Click a filter field button located at the top of a pivot chart to access a filtering dialog similar to that shown in Figure 44.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Clique em um botão de campo de filtro localizado na parte superior de um gráfico dinâmico para acessar uma caixa de diálogo de filtragem semelhante à mostrada na 44.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Change the filtering applied to the pivot table and pivot chart through this dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Altere a filtragem aplicada à tabela dinâmica e ao gráfico dinâmico por meio desta caixa de diálogo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>The right-hand section of the button’s legend indicates the filtering status, that is “- all -” when nothing is filtered, “- multiple -” when multiple but not all items are filtered, or the value when only that value is not filtered.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>A seção direita da legenda do botão indica o status de filtragem, ou seja, “- todos -” quando nada é filtrado, “- múltiplos -” quando vários, mas não todos os itens são filtrados, ou o valor quando apenas esse valor não é filtrado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Buttons located at the bottom and right of a pivot chart that include a downward pointing arrow provide access to a sorting and filtering dialog similar to the shown in Figure 36.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Os botões localizados na parte inferior e direita de um gráfico dinâmico que incluem uma seta apontando para baixo fornecem acesso a uma caixa de diálogo de ordenação e filtragem semelhante à mostrada na 36.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Change the sorting and filtering applied to the pivot table and pivot chart through this dialog.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Altere a ordenação e a filtragem aplicadas à tabela dinâmica e ao gráfico dinâmico por meio desta caixa de diálogo.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Figure 53: Filtering applied to filter and row fields</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Figura 55: Filtragem aplicada aos campos de filtro e linha</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Deleting a pivot chart</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Excluir um gráfico dinâmico</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>To delete a pivot chart, select the chart and press Del on the keyboard.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Para excluir um gráfico dinâmico, selecione o gráfico e tecle Del.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>When you delete a pivot chart, the associated pivot table is not affected.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Quando se exclui um gráfico dinâmico, a tabela dinâmica associada não é afetada.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Caution</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Cuidado</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>If you delete a pivot table with an associated pivot chart, the pivot chart is also deleted.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>Se excluir uma tabela dinâmica com um gráfico dinâmico associado, o gráfico dinâmico também será excluído.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="en">
        <seg>Calc opens a dialog box to confirm the pivot table deletion.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="pt-BR" creationid="OmegaT Aligner" creationdate="20240401T222913Z">
        <seg>O Calc abre uma caixa de diálogo para confirmar a exclusão da tabela dinâmica.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
  </body>
</tmx>
